this video is sponsored by brilliant hey
guys this looks like a fun one there's a
chord cutting the square in half and it
has a length of six and it wants to know
what is the area of the semicircle if
you want to try it on your own pause it
right now cuz I'm going to solve it in 3
2 1 the thing we're solving for is the
area of a semicircle that's going to be
equal to Pi R 2 / 2 and for the first
step I want to hide the semicircle and
focus on the Square let's take both
diagonals of the square and the
intersection of those diagonals would be
the center of the square and you can see
this also goes through the center and
that's true for any line that bisects
the square it will always go through the
center of the square and now let's focus
on the given chord the center of the
square will cut this chord in half so we
get three and three now we can bring
back the semicircle and let's focus on
the semicircle through this midpoint
let's draw a perpendicular line it's
going to be the perpendicular bis sector
of our chord and the perpendicular bis
sector of any chord will always go
through the center of a circle so we can
mark this center right here next I'm
thinking let's go back to the square and
let's take this piece right here and
extend it all the way to the end of the
square since these two are equal to
three these two will also be equal to
three and that is something else that's
universally true as long as this is
cutting the square in half and this is
perpendicular to it these portions will
always be equal to each other I'm mostly
interested in these three down here we
don't really need this one and let's
bring back our semicircle and next I
want to look at the whole circle and
let's extend this down here and this
piece will be equal to the radius that
we're trying to solve for this red
radius is equal to this blue radius
since this blue thing is equal to R and
this piece is equal to 3 that leaves Rus
3 for this little piece right here and
if we focus on this entire green length
right here it's equal to r + 3 so let's
write it as r + 3 and now we can use
another set of notes this one is about
the relationship of intersecting chords
in circles a * B will always equal C * D
and for our Circle here 3 * 3 will equal
the quantity r + 3 * the quantity Rus 3
on the left hand side 3 * 3 is equal to
9 and r + 3 * r - 3 is a difference of 2
squares it simplifies to r^ 2 - 9 and
here's the notes right here and it ends
up being a + b * Aus B is equal to a^ 2
- b^ 2 now we have 9 is equal to r^ 2 -
9 to get the r 2 by itself let's add 9
to both sides 99 + 9 is equal to 18 and
these 9es cancel each other out leaving
us with r 2 then we can square root both
sides of the equation and we get R is
equal to the < TK of 18 and this is
really all we need to find the area of
our semicircle in the place of this R we
can plug in square < TK of 18 this
square root and this Square will cancel
each other out and 18 / 2 is equal to 9
and we now have the area of our
semicircle it's equal to 9 pi unit squar
let's put a box around it I really like
this question I thought it was a
brilliant one Speaking of brilliant I
want to give you guys another update on
brilliant I've been going through
brilliant for a while now and it has
thousands of lessons to choose from and
all of them are interactive you learn by
doing this stuff I was focusing on
programming for while but now I've
returned back to more math stuff and
also data like this exploring data
visually it's interesting I've always
been fascinated by data visualization
being able to spot important trends at a
glance and making quick decisions is so
cool but you have to be careful you have
to make sure you understand the
visualizations otherwise you can make
some bad decisions there's a lot of
things you want to look out for
especially something like a manipulated
Axis or scales and I suspect a lot of
people aren't familiar with things like
log scales I think brilliant has a great
interactive way to learn about those I'm
also looking at predicting with
probability it's been a lot of fun I
haven't looked at it yet but I'm looking
forward to this Bas roll stuff one of
the only videos I ever deleted was about
base roll the video was correct but
people didn't believe it so I ended up
deleting the video maybe after I go
through this I'll come up with better
ways to explain it if you want to try
brilliant there's a free 30-day trial
just visit brilliant.org Andy or click
on the link in the description you can
also get 20% off an annual premium plan
how exciting